You have to figure out what matters. And
what we did is sit down and say, you
know, what factors into retention, it's
getting results. So, you start working
backwards from, okay, getting results.
What does that mean? Well, in the
fitness world, it's the consistency. And
so, you start to boil that down. And
four workouts is kind of where we
started that number, but then we started
to ratchet it down to three. And that
was backed by science. And ultimately,
our job then is to say, okay, how do we
get three workouts to be consistent?
Hello, I'm your host, David Bernard.
Today's conversation is shorter than
usual and will be featured in
RevenueCat's state of subscription apps
report. Each episode in this series will
explore one crucial topic and share
actionable insights from top
subscription app operators. With me
today, Ben Gam, VP of product at Ladder.
On the podcast, I talk with Ben about
productdriven retention as the
foundation for life cycle marketing,
working backward from results to nail
activation, and why talking to
individual users can lead you astray.
Hey Ben, thanks so much for joining me
on the podcast today.
>> Yeah, I'm super excited to be here. Uh,
thanks for having me. We've talked a ton
on the podcast about the kind of
blocking and tackling of retention, uh,
you know, life cycle marketing, all all
those kind of things, but what I feel
like we maybe haven't talked enough
about and why super excited to have you
on the podcast is product as retention
and finding those product levers that
actually drive retention and that being
kind of the foundation of everything
else you build on top versus thinking
that some, you know, life cycle
marketing hack, the Perfect push
notification is what's going to get you
over the hump. And so yeah, let's let's
dig into that. Let's start at a high
level. Like what is your kind of
philosophy around retention? The first
thing is retention is king. It gives you
permission to do everything else
upstream. And I think the easiest part
to start is like you know what is
retention? And you know retention is if
someone pays you, do they pay you again?
>> Yeah.
Kind of important.
>> It's very important but it's not easy,
right? The challenge is you know in the
beginning it's very volatile. Then as
you mature as a product and company, it
sort of becomes like a rubber band ball
where it's like all those rubber bands
are are influences and factors into
retention. So it's really hard to like
understand what is, you know, going into
it because it becomes very stubborn. And
so what I think really you have to do to
boil it down is you have to figure out
you know what matters and I think you
know with that you have to be able to
speak the language to the user but also
internally and you know what we did is
sit down and say you know what factors
into retention it's getting results we
went through all the fivestar results
all the people that were you know just
hands up saying like this is really you
know striking a chord and that was the
underlying theme. So you know you start
working backwards from okay getting
results what does that mean? Well, it's
in the fitness world, it's the
consistency, right? And so, you start to
boil that down and four four workouts is
kind of where we started that number,
but then we started to ratchet it down
to three. And that was backed by
science. And ultimately, our job then is
to say, okay, how do we get three
workouts to be consistent? And you know,
our ethos became and still is today,
don't make me think. Get that person in
there, they press play, they do the
workout, and if we can do that three
times a week, that is really what
ladders up to to retention. Yeah, that's
a that's such a great way to think about
it. And and you know, I think in some
ways it's maybe more obvious for a
fitness app that like the results that
you want to get are are like physical
results is like getting bigger, getting
stronger, getting fitter. Uh and those
are even maybe more objective to measure
and see. But for a lot of apps, it still
is about getting results. you know, if
you download Photo Room to enhance the
photos quality of your eBay listings,
it's like you're there to get results.
And so, I love that thinking. It's like,
you know, why are your users downloading
your app? And and like you said, it's a
great place to mine those insights are
those five star reviews. Like, why are
people excited about your app? What are
they telling other people? And then you
work backward from there versus again
thinking some like retention tactic is
what's going to drive the loop. It's
like, no, what's going to drive the loop
is getting results. So, I know at ladder
y'all have had a lot of very clear kind
of product unlocks that that started
driving that loop that were like clear
retention level levers. So, tell me
about some of those.
>> Yeah, I think the first one that comes
to mind is the journal, you know, and
you kind of hit it where, you know, the
the first question typically in
onboarding is, you know, what is your
primary goal? And you know for fitness
it's a lot of times I want to get
stronger I want to lose weight I want to
tone body I want to like look good feel
good so that's kind of you know getting
the results but how do you measure it
right and the journal is you know by
definition if if you're not familiar
with ladder basically we have a workout
player and your ability to track your
reps and weights even you know distance
for cardio and you know things like that
it is your ability to like you know put
in data and you know I think it's one of
those beautiful things that as a
consumer the user, they're able to, you
know, put in that data, but it's a
reward because downstream, it serves as
a flywheel for us, the business. You
know, you input the data, then the next
time you come in and like for that, you
know, specific movement, let's call it,
you know, an RDL or a bench press. And
the recommended weights come back into
play because we've now personalized it
by putting in that that existing weight.
And then over time, you see the
progress, right? And what's really key
for strength training is that you're
starting to lift more at least
incrementally and it can be gradual but
as you see that you see the progress you
hit PRs and it's all those you know
factors that you know really again go
back to like what is the the core piece
of this and that's getting results and
that's I think the mental and the
physical getting stronger part the
ladder can deliver on.
>> I love the way y'all integrated it into
the product as well. So, I mean, you
know, as as most podcast listeners would
know, I'm a huge ladder fan at this
point. Hit my six week streak of three
workouts a week starting the year. So,
that was one of my goals was to light up
light up the little ladder chart, which
we can talk about that more in a bit.
And so, with the journal, after each
workout, you do this little thing of
like, hey, since you started, you've
progressed this much. And just just the
other day it was like 62% increase in my
dumbbell bench press which you know a
lot of that's form and my muscle
connection and stuff like that but like
it was super encouraging to see that and
like to to get back to those like what
do people want results? Well at the end
of each workout I'm seeing the results
and it's just such a powerful little
flywheel there. So that's exactly right.
It's really much like a snowball feature
where you know the people are putting
the data in and like that's the you know
that's step one but then you start to
build out the outer layers and that's
the the reinforcement loops is saying
like hey like you're hitting that
progress at that level where you have
that PR and it's not just you know that
one movement it's all these other
movements and so it keeps like going in
that loop where you start to expand not
only you know there within the workout
but it goes outside of it where you have
like the journal history and like you're
able to see that into like your profile
And that's building state. And that is
where you start to become entrenched
into a product because, you know, it
sounds negative, but it it becomes like
powerful because you become proud of
like what you've done. And it's funny, I
was listening to a a podcast over the
past couple weeks and, you know, they
were talking about the where AI is going
to influence data and they mentioned,
you know, there's going to be some
products that are going to be sticky
because they have hostages. And I don't
like to think it about in that way
because it feels, you know, a little bit
negative, but you know, as you build
state, it becomes sticky. And there's a
reason why that that loop exists for a
lot of companies and it's powerful.
>> Yeah. I mean, I I could see as you all
layer on AI to to better inform what
your next, you know, weight should be
and things like that, it's like you've
have so much history from me now over a
year of workouts that you can then layer
on. And I don't want to lose that
progress either. It's like I've got
check marks and streaks and, you know,
progress data and all that kind of stuff
that you kind of lose if you move. So,
so yeah, the the hostage term maybe is
not the best, but it it really does kind
of effectively work like that. The next
thing I wanted to dive into was widgets
and streaks and check marks. So, huge
fan of the widget. It's right there on
my home screen. It's where I I launch
workouts from it and like I can see the
little yellow boxes light up. So, it's a
calendar and it and it it lights up the
day when you've completed a workout. I
mean, pretty typical kind of like a
streak mechanism, but it's so powerful
sitting on my home screen. So, so tell
me about those and the impact it had on
retention.
>> Yeah, I think one of the the key parts
of building out a product is you have to
figure out like the the game that exists
within the product and it has to be very
very simple. And again, if you go back
to you know the getting results and the
consistency, it was all built around
that northstar of like three workouts.
And so these are what we call
reinforcers, right? So you have the
check mark is what gives you like for a
completed workout that's you know you
have to get three of those and three of
those equal a streak for a week and then
you know the widget is what takes that
outside the app to again reinforce that.
So, as you're scrolling your phone,
subconsciously, you know, or
consciously, you're seeing that, right?
And it has a huge effect to say like,
"Oh, I need I need to remember like to
go do my third workout or there's that
sense of pride." And, you know, I think
one of the things that's underrated
about the widget, too, is, you know,
other people see that, right? It might
not happen often, but there's times
where like you're seeing as, you know,
other people are swiping their phone,
they see that widget and they're like,
"What is that?" And that can drive
conversation uh you know and referrals
uh in a way as well.
>> So do you have any sense for how many
people install the widget and how that
has impacted retention?
>> Approximately I'd say a third of people
have the the widget. It's one of those
things that benchmarks are tough. You
know I think every product has you know
different ways of doing stuff. So
whether you know a third is good or bad
it seems positive right. We've
definitely tried to increase that over
time and you know I think it matters
when you pop that you know it's it can't
be the first thing that you show you
know you haven't earned that trust but
we've tried to like position it and and
try to like you know build it out where
you know again it looks cool you give
them the instructions cuz it's not
exactly intuitive for the majority of
people I think the people listening to
this podcast you know they they all know
how to do it but the average person it's
difficult but you know once you get it
there again it's it's very very powerful
feature to serve as that billboard.
>> Yeah. And not not every app is gonna
have a way to create a meaningful widget
where people would want to have it on
their home screen, but boy, if you can
crack that, it really can be so
powerful. And a third of your users
having a billboard on their home screen
is it's pretty cool. And yeah, it's like
I don't I don't know what a benchmark
would be. I should ask more guests this
over time and people I talk to in the
industry, but yeah, if you can unlock a
that kind of billboard on the home
screen with a widget, it's it's
powerful. Do you do you actually track
and I meant to ask this with the ladder
journal as well? Do you have any stats
like were you able to track like people
who have the widget on their home
screen, you know, complete their streak
at a higher rate or and then with the
journal, you know, did you did you find
specific stats of like when you
introduced that, you did see a big bump
in in longerterm retention? Yeah, you're
able to see correlation. If you go back
to the journal, you know, we're up
upwards of, you know, around like 70 75%
of users use the uh the journal for each
workout. It didn't start there though,
right? I mean like these are the things
again you build it you build like the
core layer and then you have to build
out these amplifiers and that's where we
went upstream and you know we have
what's called a welcome workout and
that's where the coaches are able to the
voice over you know not only the
instruction of like what are you doing
why are you doing it but also layer in
those pieces to say like hey you know
pop open that journal swipe up input
those weights here's why and it's the
same thing with a widget you know able
to to really you know start to build out
make sure that people are using it and
then make sure that it has good feedback
and then you build out those peripherals
to really drive engagement.
>> Yeah, such a great point and and ladder
is an interesting case and again I don't
think every app is going to be able to
replicate some of these specific things
that ladder does to drive these
retention loops and drive this kind of
product based retention. But in ladder,
the way it works is like you you have a
real human coach that is like coaching
you through the workout with these
videos. And I mean, it's just part of
what makes the product so fantastic. But
what's so cool, and I hear it all the
time when I'm working out, is how the
coaches are just subtly dropping things
in like, "Make sure you log this in the
in the journal." You know, I'm I'm in
Team Forged with Coach Corey, and like
he'll say like, "You you should have a
weight for this exercise from last week
in the journal. check your journal. And
so, you know, again, not every app is
going to be able to, you know, have this
like, you know, real human reinforcing
these things in in those ways, but the
foundation is the same is that like when
you find those retention levers, find
ways within the product to drive usage
of those features, which then drives the
retention. And this does get a little
bit to the blocking and tackling like
that may be a push notification, that
may be an email helping people go deeper
into a feature like but you need to
build the loop first and then you build
the tactical things around it to kind of
reinforce those loops.
>> Yeah, 100%. And I I'd also say that the
one thing is that I found is like yes,
you can build those outer pieces, the
notifications and stuff and they are
very effective, but you have to really
layer these things in that the moment
like you know as they're doing stuff. So
again, that's where if you go back to
just the the example with voiceovers,
you know, you can write up, you know,
FAQs and educational content about, you
know, why the journal is important, all
that stuff. But if you're able to
communicate that while they're in the
the motion of doing it, that is 10x more
effective. And that is like one of those
really powerful things that, you know,
that's the human element that ladder
brings that is able to really again
drive a lot of the the engagement that
correlates to the retention for ladder.
Well, the last thing I wanted to touch
on was user feedback and I know that's
something that ladder takes very
seriously. So, how do you think about
feedback and integrating that into the
broader product roadmap and decision-m?
Yeah, I mean the first thing is
feedback's a gift and I know a lot of
people say that, but it it really is it
makes our jobs a lot easier. We get to
just really, you know, listen to people
like what do they actually want? And the
hard part is actually staying
disciplined and following through with
that. There's effectively three ways
that I' I've bucketed how we think about
feedback. There's one, there's like the
acute pain and that usually comes
through our Slack. There's feedback
mechanisms throughout the app that they
can just write out like, hey, I
experienced this issue. It's typically,
you know, built around that. The second
is we do a lot of surveys. There's ad
hoc, but there's recurring surveys, too.
And as an example, we we do one at the
end of the year. And, you know, we have
an insanely productive community.
There's 7,500 plus responses this past
year. it takes over 45 minutes. Thank
god for AI to be able to, you know, like
be able to parse it out and understand
what they what they want. And then the
third is dog fooding. Uh, and it's
really important. It's not a
requirement, you know, if you work at
ladder. But I think in order to like
really, you know, test drive the
product, but have that end toend mental
model of what's happening, it really
helps. And also like building it out
and, you know, delivering that empathy
for the user because you're experiencing
it too. Do you all do individual user
interviews and how how much weight do
you put on those? It
>> is a spicy take. I think they can be
helpful, but I think the problem is
especially in consumer, you have so many
people that are very diverse. You know,
they're all throughout the world and if
you talk to, you know, five or 10
people, they might weigh in on a part
that, you know, gives you a little bit
of insight, but the problem is you can't
overindex to that, right? Because they
still only represent N of five or n of
10. So these surveys are really
effective because we do them so often.
They're very, you know, there's a huge
population set and I think that's a
really to be honest like just a much
better way to kind of work backwards
from like that large amount of people as
long as you can construct those surveys
and ask questions, you know, in the
right manner that are not, you know, too
biased or leading them, you know,
towards an answer.
>> Yeah, that's that's so powerful. And I
mean, you know, again, y'all have such
an engaged community. It's probably
going to be hard for the average app to
get that many responses, especially to
that um extensive of a survey. But
again, finding ways to get that larger
breadth of feedback versus kind of
overlying on any individual feedback.
And it's so hard like you you get one
bad review in the app store that harps
on one, you know, missing product
feature and you're like, "Oh, I got to
build that and it's going to unlock
everything." But then a lot of times
it's like, "No, it's like that user
cared about that." But don't like don't
overfocus on that like one piece of bad
feedback versus what everybody else is
telling you. And one of the cool things
y'all built this year was nutrition. So
you have the kind of core strength
training app and then you layered on a
nutrition piece where if you're going to
get results even increasing strength
like you got to have your your diet and
food dialed in. But from what I
understand that was like direct like
users were screaming for I mean you know
not literally of course but in the
feedback it just felt like that was such
a strong thing. How did that come about?
>> Yeah I mean that comes directly from
that that annual survey. So I guess it
was end of 2024 you know we asked
probably 80 90 questions and again
they're multiple choice there's
open-ended but you know what came
through very clearly you know signal
from noises. They wanted nutrition and
they wanted something that again, you
know, maps to results because if you're
doing the workout, you have a dialed in
nutrition. You know, it's just again a
multiplier to get there faster and
hopefully be sustainable. So that came
through and that's something that, you
know, we looked at and from first
principles try to understand, okay, what
are the most effective methods? You
know, what exactly are they using today
and can we do this? And that was a long,
you know, project, longer than the usual
ones, but it's a big bet, right, that we
started beginning of last year and
launched, you know, a few months ago,
which has been very exciting for us.
>> Yeah. How are things going with that? I
mean, it's a funny thing, too, and I I
talked about this in one of the other
minis for the state of subscription apps
report is that sometimes users are
saying like, you know, we really want
this, we really want this, we really
want this, and then they don't actually
use it. So, how have things been going
with nutrition? Yeah, it's been going
very well. I mean, that's where, you
know, to your point, there are times
where people say stuff that doesn't map
to reality, right? And this is one, you
know, it's basically crossed 100 days
since we launched. And so, when you're
starting to like map things to
retention, it's pretty tough. So, you
have to like really compress it, you
know? So, what is like week 2, week
three, week four retention? And we're
starting to get really, you know, in the
weeds of okay, if you can go upstream,
like if you just think about nutrition
as a standalone product, how do they
log? Do they log consistently day one,
day two? Those are like those
indicators. And I think thus far we've
had a lot of really good signal that not
only is has it been effective for people
who are tracking macros, but if you
think about how it works throughout the
entire ladder ecosystem or the platform,
we call them hybrid users. Those who are
using both the workouts and nutrition,
they're driving conversion if they're
new, right? So the percentage of those
who are converting are much higher.
They're using both. And then those who
are using both as well are also much
more retentive. They're staying on the
platform. So those two have come, you
know, are true early on 100 days in. But
it's super exciting for us as a
business, you know, after such a a long
journey in big bet. Yeah. When you
invest much into something, it's great
to see it paying off. And you know,
something we talk about a ton on the
podcast is finding and unlocking that
kind of secondary product market fit.
And again, like it, you know, of course,
strength training, nutrition, like they
go so handinand and it's hard to it's
hard for a lot of apps to find that
secondary product market fit, but when
you do, it's that whole new lever of
retention. And so it it can be such a
powerful thing. As we wrap up, was there
anything else that you wanted to share
or any jobs you wanted to shout out?
I'll just say uh I think I have the best
job in the world. I get to work along
people that are fantastic, really good
at what they do. we get to solve hard
problems and you know be positive for
others in in their lives uh which is you
know very meaningful. So we're looking
to hire anyone who's um a crack or you
know a builder by nature uh product
design specifically would be great and
then also any engineers so iOS backend
front end uh reach out on LinkedIn and
you know if that's not you know your
world then would love for you to try out
Ladder and tell us what you think.
>> Awesome. And ladder is such a fun team
and I visited your office several times
because it's right up the road from me
in Austin and really cool team, really
cool people, fun headquarters. You are
hiring remote though too, right? So not
every job has to be in the Austin
office. That's correct. We have HQ in
Austin, but we're hiring remote and uh
yeah, we just have, you know, a lot of
momentum and a lot of good people and it
it's fun. So yeah, you've seen it
firsthand and uh you know, we're looking
for more, which is it's rare, too, by
the way. We do not hire often. So, um,
again, if you fit that profile, please
reach out. We'd love to talk to you.
>> Awesome. Well, thanks so much for
joining me, Ben. This was great.
>> Yeah, thank you so much, David. Cheers.
>> Thanks so much for listening. If you
have a minute, please leave a review in
your favorite podcast player. You can
also stop by chat.subclub.com
to join our private community.